Finding Aid for the Paul Alexander Bartlett Papers, 1923-1990 LSC.2106
UCLA Library Special Collections
Paul Alexander Bartlett papers
1923-1990
UCLA Library Special Collections
Bartlett, Paul Alexander
LSC.2106
4.5 Linear Feet (9 boxes)
Paul Alexander Bartlett (1909- ) was born in Moberly, Missouri, and raised in Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan. He was an instructor in creative writing at Georgia State College (1955) and editor of publications at the University of California Santa Barbara (1964-70). Bartlett contributed short stories and poetry to magazines and anthologies. His published books include: Adios, mi México, and When the Owl Cries. The collection consists of literary manuscripts, correspondence, research notes, published works, ephemera, diaries, photograph albums and genealogy materials of Paul Alexander Bartlett. Correspondents include John Dos Passos, James Michener, Upton Sinclair, and Frank Tannenbaum.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Paul Alexander Bartlett, 1981 & 1984.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942303613606533
Biography
Bartlett was born on June 13, 1909 in Moberly, Missouri, and raised in Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan; BA, Oberlin College, 1932; also attended University of Arizona, and later studied art at the National University of Mexico and in Guadalajara; instructor in creative writing, Georgia State College, 1955; editor of publications, University of California Santa Barbara, 1964-70; contributed short stories and poetry to magazines and anthologies; published books include Adios, mi México, and When the Owl Cries.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of literary manuscripts, correspondence, research notes, published works, ephemera, diaries, photograph albums and genealogy materials of writer Paul Alexander Bartlett. Correspondents include John Dos Passos, James Michener, Upton Sinclair, and Frank Tannenbaum.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Manuscripts by PAB and related material (Boxes 1-2).
Correspondence (Boxes 2,8).
Journals by PAB (Boxes 3-5).
Poetry and miscellaneous prose by PAB, photograph albums, genealogy material (Box 6).
Unpublished writings (Boxes 6-7).
Published writings (Boxes 7-9).
Related Material
Paul Alexander Bartlett Collection of Submissions to the Literary Annual, Workshop (Collection 926). Available at Department of Special Collections, University Research Library, University of California, Los Angeles.
Poets, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Manuscripts for publication; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Archives.; Diaries.; Bartlett, Paul Alexander--Archives.
- Manuscripts by Paul Bartlett and Related Material
  - Notebook: Source data for Forward, Children! v.p., v.d..; ca. 150 leaves. (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    Correspondence, notes, postcards, photographs, pamphlets.
  - Forward, Children! n.p., n.d.; 182 leaves. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reviews and comments re Forward, Children!, 5 leaves. Typescript, typescript (carbon), photocopy. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Journal of Leonardo da Vinci. San Diego., 1977.; 170 leaves. Typescript, photocopy. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    With this: ephemera. 1 item.
  - Maelstrom. n.p., n.d.; 267 leaves. Typescript. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mexican Footprints. n.p., n.d.; 271 leaves. Typescript, typescript (carbon). Bound. Signed by the author. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    With this: photocopy of foreword by Don M. Wolfe.
  - The Mexican Haciendas by Paul Alexander Bartlett. n.p., 83 leaves. Typescript, typescript (carbon), photocopy. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Spokes for Memory. n.p., 1977-1978.; 140 leaves. Typescript, typescript (carbon), photocopy. Signed by the author. (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Spokes for Memory. Bartlett, Paul Alexander. Baltimore: Icarus Press, c., 1979.; Papers. Signed by the author. (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - To Reason Why. n.p., n.d.; 249 leaves. Typescript, typescript (carbon), Bound. Signed by the author. (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - When the Owl Cries. Ephemera. v.p., v.d.; 28 items. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Includes dustjacket of the book, clippings, photocopies of clippings.
    General note
    First published by Macmillan, 1960.
  - Correspondence. v.p., v.d.; 10 items. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    Adamas, J. Donald. 1 item.
    Barnstone, Willis. 1 item
    Dietrich, Susan. 1 item.
    Dos Passos, John. 1 item.
    Fraenkel, Michael. 1 item.
    Gorman, Herbert. 1 item.
    Ippolito, Donald. 1 item.
    Roeder, Ralph. 1 item.
    Sinclair, Upton. 1 item.
    Walsh, Richard J. 1 item.
    NOTE: The letters are photocopies, not original letters.
  - Publications, (3 items) (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - The Greyledge Review. Chickering, by Paul Alexander Bartlett, Fall 1979.
    - Bartlett, Paul Alexander. Adios, mi Mexico. San Diego, Autograph Editions, c., 1979.; Paper. Signed by author.
    - Bartlett, Paul Alexander. Wherehill. Colima, Mexico. Autograph Editions, 1975.; Paper. no. 95/100. Signed by the author.
  - Ephemera re Paul Bartlett., 5 items. (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence
  - Adams, J. Donald., April 10, 1946; December 11, 1947.; 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    All letters are photocopies except for 1 item in folder 32.
  - Abramson, Ben (Argus Book Shop)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    July 26, 1939.
  - Babelon, Jean., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    June 7, 1967.
  - Balch, Earle (G.P. Putnam's Sons.)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    June 13, 1940.
  - Barnstone, Willis., 9 items. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    December 26, 1962
    March 30,1963
    April 29, 1963
    October 4, 1963
    November 10, 1963
    December 8, 1963
    July 27, 1966
    May 30, 1968, February 6, n.d.
  - Beals, Carleton., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    December 28, 1950.
  - Chase, Stuart., 3 items. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    September 26, 1956
    January 16, 1967
    January 28, 1972
  - Cole, Lois Dwight (The MacMillan Company)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    March 5, 1935.
  - Conroy, Jack., 4 items. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    September 27, 1962
    November 4, 1962
    September 28, 1971
    April 9, 1975
  - De Conde, Alex., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    February 1, 1972
    December 12, 1973
  - Dos Passos, John., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    September 15, 1952
    September 23, 1952
  - Eoyang, Eugene (Doubleday & Company Incorporated)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    November 13, 1963.
  - Fillmore, Louise (Macdowell Associates)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 22)
    May 10, 1949.
  - Fraenkel, Michael., 1 item (& 1 copy). (Box 8, Folder 23)
    September 10, 1950 (With another copy).
  - Gardner, David Pierpont., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 24)
    July 11, 1973.
  - Gessler, Clifford. 2 items (& 2 copies). (Box 8, Folder 25)
    November 25, 1947 (2 copies)
    December 8, 1950
  - Gorman, Herbert, 3 items (& 2 copies). (Box 8, Folder 26)
    March 5, 1940
    July 11, 1948 (and 2 copies)
    May 3, 1949
  - Hicks, Granville., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 27)
    March 27, 1970.
  - Kerr, Chester (Harcourt, Brace & Company)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 28)
    October 26, 1939.
  - Kirk, Russell (The University Bookman)., 9 items. (Box 8, Folder 29)
    April 26, 1963
    April 18, 1965
    January 3, 1968
    June 5, 1969
    November 14, 1973
    February 18, 1974
    April 7, 1974
    December 5, 1975
    August 15, 1982
  - Matthews, Diane., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 30)
    26 March 1973.
  - Maxwell, Allen (Southwest Review)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 31)
    February 5, 1948.
  - Mayer, John (Farrar, Straus & Company)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 32)
    March 16, 1949 (original letter)
    March 16, 1949 to MacDowell Colony.
  - Michener, James., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 33)
    April 18, 1988
    June 7, 1988
  - Montgomery, Rutherford., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 34)
    May 3, 1963.
  - Pearce, Charles., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 35)
    September 14, 1935.
  - Phillips, Howard S. (Mexican Life)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 36)
    April 18, 1944
    June 15, 1971
  - Poland, Reginald. (Atlanta Art Associates)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 37)
    September 4, 1959
    March 23, 1961
  - Powell, Desmond (Arizona Quarterly)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 38)
    October 22, 1948.
  - Quinn, Kerker (Accent)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 39)
    May 13, 1944.
  - Ransom, John Crowe (The Kenyon Review)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 40)
    March 8, 1948 (and 1 copy).
  - Roeder, Ralph., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 41)
    November 14, 1950
    July 28, 1951
  - Rothenberg, William L. (Carnegie Fund for Authors)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 42)
    May 10, 1961
    January 25, 1973
  - Stokes Company (Frederick A.)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 43)
    September 1, 1939
    January 8, 1940
  - Sinclair, Upton., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 44)
    February 18, 1952 (and another copy)
    March 21, 1952
  - Tannenbaum, Frank., 5 items. (Box 8, Folder 45)
    October 5, 1950
    May 28, 1954
    November 16, 1955
    October 18, 1961
    May 8, 1963.
  - Tillotson, M.R. (National Park Service)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 46)
    March 31, 1936.
  - Tomasic, Irene., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 47)
    n.d.
  - Trutner, Kathryn (Doubleday, Doran & Company)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 48)
    January 30, 1933.
  - Unwin, Stanley (Allen & Unwin Ltd.)., 2 items. (Box 8, Folder 49)
    March 9, 1942 (Unwin to PAB)
    January 18, 1939 (copy of transcript only from Ford Madox Ford to Unwin)
  - Walsh, Mrs. Richard J., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 50)
    February 16, 1951.
  - Wheelock, John Hall (Charles Scribner's sons)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 51)
    April 10, 1951.
  - Woodburn, John., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 52)
    August 3, 1945.
  - Wolfe, Don M., 3 items. (Box 8, Folder 53)
    June 25, 1970
    May 20, 1971 (DMW to John Meyer)
    May 20, 1971 (DMW to PAB)
  - Zavala, Silvio., 4 items. (Box 8, Folder 54)
    May 13, 1953
    December 12, 1966
    December 5, 1973
    July 3, 1974
  - Zuno, Jose G. (Escuela de Bells Artes)., 1 item. (Box 8, Folder 55)
    August 25, 1949.
- Journals by PAB
  - Journals by Paul Bartlett, 1923-1948
    (Additions, November 1984)
    - 1923., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1925., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1928., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1926-1928., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1928-1940., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - 1942., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1942., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - 1943., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1944., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - 1947., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1948., 1 item. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Journals by Paul Bartlett, 1949-1972
    - 1950., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1949., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1951-1952., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1953., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1954., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1955-1956., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1956-1960., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1963-1964., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1965-1968., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1969-1970., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1970-1971., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1971., 1 item. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Journals by Paul Bartlett, 1973-1983
    - 1973., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1974., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1975., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1977-1978., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1979., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1978-1979., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1979., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1979-1980., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1980., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1980-1981., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1981., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1982., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1982., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1983., 1 item. (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Poetry and Miscellaneous Prose by PAB, Photograph Albums, genealogy Material
  - Poetry and miscellaneous prose pieces by Paul Bartlett. v.p., 1941-1948.; ca. 100 leaves. Holograph. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Photograph Albums, (2 items)
    - 1923-1943., 1 item. (Box 6, Folder 2)
      Generally family photographs.
    - Mexico, 1941-1942.; 2 items. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - genealogy Material, (3 items)
    - Bartlett coat of arms (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Postcard, 1660 (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Bartlett House, Manomet. Plymouth, Massachusetts.
    - Bartlett, Robert Merrill. Pilbrim Robert Bartlett (1603-1676) and some of his descendants, c., 1966.; 26pp. (Box 6, Folder 3)
      Plymoth, Massachusetts: Society of the Descendants of Robert Bartlett of Plymoth, Incorporated.
- Unpublished Writings by PAB
  - The White Cactus. Santa Barbara, n.d., 232pp. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    Bound Typescript with list of the author's publications.
  - Black Aspirins. San Diego, n.d., 233pp. Typescript with some photocopy pages. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    With original pen and ink illustration for frontispiece.
  - Wherehill. San Diego, n.d., 222pp. Photocopy of typescript. (Box 7, Folder 2)
    With typescript preface laid in novel and holograph memoir, Christmas at Wherehill [incomplete].
    With original pen & ink illustration My father's world signed by PAB.
  - The H-Man. San Diego, 1982.; 240pp. Photocopy of typescript. (Box 7, Folder 3)
    With list of publications, copies of reviews of When the Owl Cries and a letter of re transmittal to an unnamed publisher.
  - Tepui. n.p., June 11, 1989., 32pp. Photocopy of typescript and holograph manuscript. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    PAB's last work.
  - Short Story
    - Exile. n.p., n.d., 6pp. Photocopy of typescript manuscript. (Box 8, Folder 9)
      Unpublished?
  - Trio
    - Burning Glass. San Diego, April 9, 1985.; 63pp. Typescript and photocopy of typescript. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      Part two of Bartlett's unpublished Trio. Original manuscript is at the American Heritage Center.
    - Campeta. n.p., revised by PAB, March 27, 1989.; 69pp. Photocopy of typescript and holograph manuscript. (Box 7, Folder 5)
      With copies of 7 pen and ink illustrations by PAB. Part 3 of PAB's Trio. The original manuscript is at the American Heritage Center.
  - Voices From the Past
    - Christ's Journal. n.p., n.d., 124pp. Photocopy of typescript on yellow paper. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Shakespeare's Journal: A Film Novel. Colima, Mexico, n.d., 227pp. Bound typescript with holograph corrections. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Abraham Lincoln's Journal. San Diego, n.d., 179pp. Typescript title page & list of quotations. Photocopy of typed manuscript. (Box 6, Folder 6)
      With reproduction of Gettysburg Address and original pen and ink sketch by PAB for frontispiece.
- Published Writings by PAB
  - The Haciendas of Mexico. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    Folder of background materials. Published by University of Colorado Press, 1990.
  - The Haciendas of Mexico. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Proof copy. Corrected April 17, 1989.
  - When the Owl Cries. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Reviews and excerpts from reviews, ca. 1960-1961, on oversize pasteup board.
  - Non-Fiction
    - The Hacienda Mansions. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Mexican Life, vol.46 no.4 (April 1970), pp.11-12.
  - Short Story
    - Chickering. (Box 8, Folder 1)
      Unusual, 1955, pp.27-32.
    - Ancient Seeds. (Box 8, Folder 2)
      Southwest Review, (Winter 1958), pp.37-45.
    - Diosbotic. (Box 8, Folder 3)
      Mexican Life, vol.45 no.3 (March 1979), pp.7-8.
    - The Inner Ear. (Box 8, Folder 5)
      Mexican Life, vol.46 no.11 (November 1970), pp.7-8.
    - The Inner Ear. (Box 8, Folder 6)
      Southwest Review, vol.67 no.3 (Summer 1982), pp.282-286.
    - Against the Wall. (Box 8, Folder 7)
      Dalhousie Review, (Winter 1983), pp.651-658. Photocopy of published story.
    - The Last Gun. (Box 8, Folder 8)
      Wind Magazine, vol.15 no.55 (1985), pp.54-60. Photocopy of published story.